Guide to the Edward Brodnax Hicks papers, 1800-1913 RL.10117
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Edward Brodnax Hicks papers
1800-1913
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hicks, Edward Brodnax
RL.10117
4 Linear Feet 6 boxes; 7 volumes; approximately 3,516 items
Edward Brodnax Hicks (1800-1858) was a lawyer, sheriff, and plantation owner from Lawrenceville, Brunswick County, Virginia. Collection comprises correspondence, legal documents, mercantile records, notes, and other papers, of Hicks and of his son, David S. Hicks, planter, lawyer, land agent, and judge in the same locality. The material relates to legal and judicial activities, Texas land deals, economic conditions in Virginia, and the Atlantic and Danville Railway Co. Included also is an extensive series of letters and papers relating to the operation, in partnership with John W. Paup, of Spring Hill plantation on the Red River, Arkansas, after 1837. An early letter, 1840, describes the deaths ("losses") of enslaved persons at the plantation, and the building of better quarters. Letters also show that Hicks engaged in selling enslaved persons at New Orleans during 1852. Correspondents include Thomas Ewing, D.J. Claiborne, Jr., Leigh R. Page, John W. Paup, and Lewis Taylor.
Biographical note
Edward Brodnax Hicks (1800-1858) was a sheriff and plantation owner of Lawrenceville, Brunswick County, Virginia. He was also superintendent of schools for a time. His son and successor to the estate and law practice, David Hicks, was a judge, sheriff, land agent, lawyer, and planter in the same locality. In 1870 he was engaged with Turnbull in selling Brunswick County land to Northerners and there is some correspondence on this matter. In 1878, David became County Judge of Brunswick County, and in the same year the letters show him as a partner in the Brunswick Land Company, engaged in land negotiations in Texas. In 1896 he was made trustee of this company, having all the land it owned put in his charge. David S. Hicks had at least three children: Rowena, Bessie, and David Jr., who was in 1894 engaged with Thomas B. Price in the lumber business in Lawrenceville.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Edward Hicks Brodnax papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1943 and 2020.
Collection Overview
Collection includes business, personal, and legal correspondence of Edward B. Hicks (died 1858), lawyer and planter of Lawrenceville, Brunswick County, Virginia, and of his son, David S. Hicks, lawyer, planter, and land agent. Papers of Edward B. Hicks include jockey club dues, records connected with his duties as sheriff in 1821 and possibly later, and with Hicks' position as superintendent of schools in Brunswick County in 1847.
Included also is an extensive series of letters and papers relating to the operation, in partnership with John W. Paup, of Spring Hill plantation at Red River, Arkansas, in 1837 and later. An early letter, 1840, describes the deaths ("losses") of enslaved persons at the plantation, and the building of better quarters. Letters also show that Hicks engaged in selling enslaved persons in New Orleans during 1852. Other interesting letters are from Lewis Taylor on the War of 1812 and another, in 1817, relative to disturbances at Princeton College, Princeton, New Jersey, caused by refusal of professors to accept state bank notes.
Centering around David S. Hicks, the papers dated after 1858 are largely legal documents, notes, and correspondence concerned with his law practice and the administration of the estate of Edward R. Hicks. The most continuous series among these legal papers is a set of letters from Leigh R. Page, a Richmond attorney. Papers also pertain to the efforts of Hicks and one Turnbull to sell lands in Brunswick County to Northerners.
Included also are records of Hicks's activities as judge of Brunswick County, as dealer in Texas lands, and as an organizer of the Atlantic and Danville Railroad. One letter, June 30, 1866, from D. J. Claiborne, Jr., concerns African American congressmen in the South and his hatred for them amidst fears of a "Negro supremacy." Fifteen letters from General Thomas Ewing are concerned with the Atlantic and Danville Railroad Company.
The volumes, generally mercantile records, seem to have into the collection as a result of Hicks's legal practice and duties as sheriff in Virginia. These are chiefly in the form of account and ledger books.
Enslaved persons -- Arkansas; Judges -- Correspondence; Judges -- Virginia -- Brunswick County; Lawyers -- Virginia -- Lawrenceville; Lawyers -- Correspondence; Plantation owners -- Correspondence; Plantations -- Arkansas; Plantations -- Economic aspects; Real estate business -- Texas; Railroads -- Virginia; Slavery -- Arkansas; Slavery -- Virginia; Arkansas -- Hempstead County -- History; Virginia -- Brunswick County -- History; Virginia -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Account books; Ledgers (account books); Atlantic and Danville Railway Company; Page, Leigh R.; Claiborne, D. J., Jr.; Ewing, Thomas
- Correspondence, 1800-1913 and undated
  - Correspondence, 1800-1849 (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    One letter from November 13, 1840, recently added to the original collection, was written from John Paup, Spring Hill Plantation, Hempstead county, Arkansas, to Edward Brodnax Hicks, his partner in the plantation and resident of Brunswick County, Virginia. His thee-page letter refers to the economics of enslaved labor and buying enslaved persons; illness and the deaths of enslaved persons on the plantation; the cotton crop, insurance, and prices; and the survey of the border between Arkansas and the Republic of Texas.
  - Correspondence, 1850-1859 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence, 1857-1861 (Box 3)
    Much of the correspondence on and after 1858 concerns the estate and death of Edward Hicks and the related activities of his son, David S. Hicks.
  - Correspondence, 1872-1877 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1878-1894 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1895-1913; undated (Box 6)
- Account and Ledger Books, 1820-1869
  These account and ledger books seem to all originate from the Lawrenceville, Virginia area, and were generated by small mercantile businesses such as general stores. The owners of some of the ledgers have not been identified.
  - Account book, 1826-1869 (Volume L:1740)
    An account book from 1864 bears the names Hicks, Jones, and Mallory, and appears to be records of a tanyard.
  - Day book, 1820-1835 (Volume F:1741)
    Two of these daybooks (1821-1828) belonged to Edward Brodnax Hicks.
  - Day book, 1835-1844 (Volume F:1742)
  - Day book, 1850-1854 (Volume F:1743)
  - Day book, 1866 (Volume F:1744)
  - Ledger, 1821-1828 (Volume F:1745)
  - Ledger, 1827-1850 (Volume F:1746)
  - Ledger, 1850-1857 (Volume F:1747)
  - Ledger, 1867 (Volume F:1750)
  - Ledger, 1868 (Volume F:1751)